Preliminary Guide to the Leslie A. Falk Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Leslie A. Falk papers
1926-1995
MS 1652
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
27
(30 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, and subject files which document Leslie A. Falk's career as area medical administrator for the United Mine Workers Health and Welfare Fund, teacher at the University of Pittsburgh Graduate School of Public Health and Meharry Medical College, and medical activist. The papers highlight Falk's interests in community health services, occupational health and safety, the delivery of medical care in other countries, and African-American medical history. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Falk, Leslie A. (Leslie Alan), 1915-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Leslie A. Falk, 1993-1994,1996, and 2000. Gift of the Estate of Leslie A. Falk, 2005.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged by accession.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, and subject files which document Leslie A. Falk's career as area medical administrator for the United Mine Workers Health and Welfare Fund, teacher at the University of Pittsburgh Graduate School of Public Health and Meharry Medical College, and medical activist. The papers highlight Falk's interests in community health services, occupational health and safety, the delivery of medical care in other countries, and African-American medical history. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
African Americans -- Medical care; Community health services; Medical care; Public health; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Falk, Leslie A. (Leslie Alan), 1915-; Weinerman, E. Richard (Edwin Richard), 1917-1970; Meharry Medical College; United Mine Workers of America; University of Pittsburgh. Graduate School of Public Health
- Original Accession, Circa 1943-1993; Accession 1994-M-042
  Scope and Contents
  Received from: Leslie A. Falk, 1993 November 5
  20 linear feet (16 boxes)
  These papers consist almost entirely of subject files, including correspondence, writings, reports, articles, clippings, notes, and other material, which date from Leslie A. Falk's career as a medical administrator for the United Mine Workers Health and Welfare Fund, teacher at the University of Pittsburgh Graduate School of Public Health and Meharry Medical College, and medical activist. The papers highlight Falk's interests in community health services, occupational health and safety, the delivery of medical care in the United States and other countries, and African-American medical history. Further information on Falk's career can be found in the manuscript draft of an autobiography, which is housed in box 16.
  - Medical care (general) (Box 1)
  - Antibiotics, polio (Box 1)
  - Occupational health and safety (Box 1)
  - Occupational health and safety (Box 2)
  - United Mine Workers of America (Box 3)
  - United Mine Workers of America (Box 4)
  - United Mine Workers of America (Box 5)
  - University of Pittsburgh. School of Public Health (Box 5)
  - Amalgamated Food Employees Union (Box 5)
  - Other countries: Britain; Eastern Europe; Central America; Kuwait (Box 6)
  - China (Box 7)
  - China (Box 8)
  - Indo-China (Box 8)
  - Meharry Medical College (Box 9)
  - Nashville (Box 9)
  - Tennessee (Box 9)
  - History of Medicine (general) (Box 10)
  - Black history and black medical history (Box 10)
  - Weinerman, Richard (Box 11)
  - Medical Committee for Human Rights (Box 12)
  - Association of Teachers of Preventive Medicine (Box 12)
  - International Physicians for the Prevention of Nuclear War (Box 12)
  - Physicians for Nuclear Responsibility (Box 12)
  - Physicians Forum (Box 12)
  - Vermont (Box 13)
  - To be sorted (Box 13)
  - Personal and corporate name file (Box 14)
  - Personal and family papers (Box 15)
  - Writings (Box 16)
- Additional material, 1926-1994; Accession 1995-M-033
  Received from: Leslie A. Falk, 1994 September 19
  1 linear feet (1 box)
  - Notes for manuscripts (Box 1)
  - James McCune Smith research (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Music class (Box 1)
  - Johns Hopkins reunion (Box 1)
  - Publishing info (Box 1)
  - Wake-Robin (Box 1)
  - Yolanda Huet-Vaughn (Box 1)
  - Soviets, Meet Middle America (Box 1)
  - Health Caravans (Box 1)
  - File donations (Box 1)
  - Health care issues (Box 1)
  - International Physicians for the Prevention of Nuclear War (Box 1)
  - Blake Gould: Health Care for the Whole Person (Box 1)
  - Sufei Ma Haide (Box 1)
  - 79th birthday (Box 1)
  - Right to Know Victory Party (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Terence Carroll (Box 1)
  - Geico (Box 1)
  - Joseph W. Houston (Box 1)
  - Leslie Falk: medical records (Box 1)
  - Letter to the editor (Box 1)
  - Meharry (Box 1)
  - Harriet Hardy (Box 1)
  - Nashville (Box 1)
  - Freeman family (Box 1)
  - Mexican-Americans (Box 1)
  - Medical Education of the Negro (Box 1)
  - Arthritis Foundation (Box 1)
  - Art (Box 1)
  - Neighborhood Education Project, Nashville (Box 1)
  - Community Advisory Board minutes (Box 1)
  - Physicians for Social Responsibility (Box 1)
  - Age information (Box 1)
- Additional material, 1970s-1995; Accession 1996-M-097
  - Herbal information and treatments, undated (Box 1)
  - Racism, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Wake Robin, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Meharry Medical College information, 1992-1994 (Box 1)
  - Matthew Walker Health Center, 1970s-1980s (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Outgoing, 1992-1994 (Box 1)
    - Incoming, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
- Additional material, Accession 2001-M-024
  - Lysozyme experiments [research data], 1937-1938 (Box 1)
  - Actions of Certain Bacteriolytic Principles [thesis], 1940 (Box 1)
  - Sigerist, Henry [correspondence and writings], 1943-1959 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1991-1993 (Box 1)
  - Writings, 1991, undated (Box 1)
- Additional material, Accession 2005-M-085
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - Trip to Russia [includes journal, photographs], 1946-1947 (Box 1)
  - Early correspondence [primarily to parents], 1937-1941 (Box 2)
  - Early personal/professional files [includes "Health Care for All: A Life in Social Medicine"], 1940-1960s (Box 3)
  - Professional files [includes reprints, correspondence, and subject files], 1960s-1990s (Box 4–7)
  - Black history research, 1980s, undated (Box 8–10)
  - Miscellaneous audiocassettes, undated (Box 11)